Guide to the Montana State Board of Entomology Records 1905-1966
Montana Historical Society
Montana State Board Of Entomology Records
1905-1966
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 28
Montana State Board of Entomology
6 linear feet of shelf space
The Montana State Board of Entomology and the Montana State Board of Health studied Rocky Mountain spotted fever (also known as tick fever) in the Bitterroot Valley. Records of the State Board of Entomology consist of correspondence (1909-1954) of State Entomologist R.A. Cooley and others; minutes (1913-1949); reports (1909-1949); subject files; writings; and miscellany. Records of the State Board of Health consist of correspondence (1908-1957) concerning the Rocky Mountain Laboratory and spotted fever; reports (1929-1956); subject files (1911-1966) concerning a wide variety of health issues including conditions on the Montana Indian reservations, the Montana Public Health Association, spotted fever; and miscellany.
The Montana State Board of Health was created by the state legislature in 1901. One of the first diseases the Board was asked to study was Rocky Mountain Spotted Fever (also known as tick fever, since the disease is spread by wood ticks) which was occurring in the Bitterroot Valley. Early work with the disease was done by Dr. T.D. Tuttle of the State Board of Health and Dr. Howard T. Ricketts, who was sponsored by the American Medical Association in 1906, and by the Montana legislature in succeeding years. Work on ticks and their control by "dipping" domestic animals and the killing of rodents upon which tick lived was done at Montana Agricultural College and Experiment Station in Bozeman by Dr. R.A. Cooley. In 1913 the Montana State Board of Entomology was created and charged with studying Rocky Mountain Spotted Fever and methods for its control. The Board was composed of the secretary of the State Board of Health (serving as chairman), the state veterinarian, and the state entomologist (serving as secretary). During the years from 1913 to 1931, the membership of the Board was W.F. Cogswell, W.J. Butler, and R.A. Cooley. Dr. Cooley also conducted tick research in Africa in the 1920s. R.R. Parker served as assistant entomologist and conducted field research on ticks from 1915 until 1922. Throughout the early years of research on tick fever, representatives from the United States Public Health Service worked in Montana in cooperation with the State Board of Health and the State Board of Entomology. In 1927 the Montana Legislative Assembly appropriated $60,000 for the construction of a laboratory in Hamilton to provide facilities for the study of the disease and the search for vaccines to prevent the disease. In 1930 the state Boards assisted in the formation of the Rocky Mountain Spotted Fever Committee composed to representatives from other states having documented cases of the disease. This committee requested that the United States Public Health Service "take over and assume full control of investigations of tick-borne, human diseases." In 1932 the laboratory facilities at Hamilton were sold to the federal government and work on tick fever was continued by federal employees.
These records are organized into two subgroups: the Montana State Board of Entomology and the Montana State Board of Health. The Montana State Board of Entomology Records include general correspondence (1909-1954), primarily between State Entomologist R.A. Cooley and other members of the State Board of Entomology (W.G. Cogswell, W.J. Butler); employees of the Board such as field researchers (Fred A. Morton, Glen M. Kohls, A.E. Seamons, Clifford Corkins, Elmer Fessler, F.J. O'Donnell, F.B. Linfield, Roscoe W. Wells); representatives from the United States Board of Entomology, U.S. Department of Agriculture, and U.S. Public Health Service (F.C. Bishop, L.D. Fricks, W.D. Hunter, L.O. Howard, W.V. King, H.P. Wood); scientists working on tick diseases (including requests for tick specimens); Montanans and public health officials requesting information about the disease; etc. This correspondence is arranged as it was kept by Dr. Cooley, by correspondent. There is also correspondence of W.G. Cogswell as chairman of the State Board of Entomology and R.R. Parker as assistant entomologist. The subgroup also includes court papers (1913); financial records (1932-1941); minutes of the Board (1913-1949); organizational materials (1913-1940); reports (1909-1949), including those of field researchers and the Board's monthly and annual reports; subject files (1927-1954); writings (1912-1937) of W.J. Butler, R.A. Cooley, R.R. Parker, and others; miscellany (1905-1938); and clippings (1908-1943). The Montana State Board of Health subgroup includes T.D. Tuttle's correspondence (1908-1912) about Rocky Mountain spotted fever and other correspondence (1919-1957) concerning the Rocky Mountain Laboratory, diseases, etc.; financial records (1912); reports (1929-1956) concerning typhoid fever, polio vaccine, etc.; subject files (1914-1966) including materials on bubonic plague, leprosy, and health conditions on Indian reservations in the state; and miscellany (1911, 1929). Printed materials and maps, photographs, and artifacts have been separated from these records and transferred to the Library, Photo Archives, and Museum respectively.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Assiniboine Indians--Health and welfare--Montana; Atsina Indians--Health and welfare--Montana; Crow Indians--Health and welfare--Montana; Dakota Indians--Health and welfare--Montana; Landless Indians--Health and welfare--Montana; Medicine--Research; Public health--Montana; Research--Montana; Rocky Mountain spotted fever; Salish Indians--Health and welfare--Montana; Tick-borne diseases; Dakota Indians--Health and welfare--Montana; Assiniboine Indians--Health and welfare--Montana
Florence (Mont.); Fort Belknap Indian Reservation (Mont.); Fort Peck Indian Reservation (Mont.); Northern Cheyenne Indian Reservation (Mont.); Powderville (Mont.); Rocky Boys Indian Reservation (Mont.)
Montana; Medicine and Health; Native Americans
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Montana State Board Of Entomology
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and F. C. Bishop (includes tick analysis data), 1910-1931 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and W. J. Butler (includes correspondence with Deputy State Veterinarian C. H. Stevens; F. J. O'Donnell), 1913-1931 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and W. F. Cogswell, 1913-1925 (Box-folder 1 / 3-4)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and W. F. Cogswell (includes correspondence of F. J. O'Donnell), 1926-1932, 1935 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and W. F. Cogswell, 1930-1932 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and L. D. Fricks, 1913-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and L. O. Howard (chief, U. S. Bureau of Entomology), 1910-1931 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and W. D. Hunter, 1909-1918 (Box-folder 1 / 9-14)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and W. V. King (includes correspondence to King from W. D. Hunter), 1909 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and W. V. King, 1910-1918, 1922, 1929 (Box-folder 1 / 16-20)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and R. R. Parker, 1911-1921 (Box-folder 1 / 21-29)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and R. R. Parker, 1922-1931, 1936 (Box-folder 2 / 1-3)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and T. D. Tuttle, 1908-1911 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and Roscoe W. Wells, 1914-1917 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and S. B. Wolbach, 1915-1931 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and H. P. Wood, 1913-1914 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and Fred A. Morton, Glen M. Kohls, A. E. Seamons, Clifford Corkins, Elmer Fessler, F. J. O'Donnell, F. B. Linfield (includes tick data), 1910-1931 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and H. T. Fernald, H. T. Ricketts, J. J. Moore, Joseph Bequaert, E. D. Germain, W. A. Hooker, W. D. Pierce, I. U. Temple, A. H. McCray, J. L. Todd, E. V. Cowdry, 1909-1928 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and the Biological Survey (U. S. Department of Agriculture Bureau of Biological Survey; includes correspondence with C. Hart Merriam, Clarence Birdseye, A. X. Fisher, H. W. Henshaw, H. W. Grayvill, and R. R. Spencer; arranged chronologically), 1910-1931 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and Montana State Officials (including Attorney General D. M. Kelly; Congressional representatives John Evans, Henry Myers, Thomas Walsh, Jeannette Rankin, W. E. McMurry, Tom Stout, Fred Whiteside; Governors EdwinNorris, S. V. Stewart; State Fish and Game Wardens J. L. DeHart, Henry Avare; State Land Board secretary; R. H. Cather at Montana State Hospital), 1909-1931 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and Numerous Persons in the Bitterrot Valley (requests for information from individuals, chambers of commerce, local businesses, etc.; arranged alphabetically), 1909-1931; 1944 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and Numerous Persons in Montana outside of the Bitterroot Valley (requests for information, etc.; arranged alphabetically), 1909-1931 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and Numerous Persons in United States outside of Montana (includes correspondence with public health officials, universities, etc.; arranged alphabetically by state), 1909-1931 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and Numerous Persons in Foreign Countries including G. H. F. Nuttall, Cecil Warburton, E. Brumpt, Eric Hearle, Hideyo Noguchi, etc. (also includes Seymour Hadwen, P. A. Buxton, David Miller, and others from Australia, New Zealand, South America, Japan, India, and the Canal Zone), 1913-1932 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
    - Correspondence between R. A. Cooley and Numerous Persons Growing Out of Tick Parasite Work Done in the Union of South Africa and the Province and Protectorate of Kenya (includes Cooley's paper "Africa" given to the Q. K. Club of Bozeman; Fred A. Morton correspondence concerning ticks shipped to U. S.; reports on foreign tick studies; etc.), 1928-1932 (Box-folder 2 / 16-17)
    - Correspondence between W. F. Cogswell and L. D. Fricks, S. B. Wolbach, H. L. Myers, H. S. Ccumming, Thomas Parran, Hidayo Noguchi, A. L. Strand, and others re Rocky Mountain spotted fever, 1913-1947 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
    - Correspondence between R. R. Parker and F. C. Bishop, W. J. Butler, W. F. Cogswell, L. D. Fricks, L. O. Howard, B. K. Kilboure, W. V. King, F. J. O'Donnell, R. R. Spencer, A. L. Strand, S. B. Wolbach, and others re Rocky Mountain spotted fever, 1915-1949 (Box-folder 2 / 19)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence re Rocky Mountain spotted fever; grasshopper control, 1919-1954 (Box-folder 2 / 20)
    - Mosquito problem at Orphan's Home, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 21)
  - Court Papers
    - John Dunbar vs Dr. Frick, Dr. R. A. Cooley and Dr. W. F. Cogswell (complaint for damages re malicious mischief charge), 1913 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
  - Financial Records
    - Parasite Fund Expenditures, Receipts, 1932-1941 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
  - Minutes
    - Montana State Board of Entomology, 1913-1949 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
  - Organization
    - History, work plans, legislative purpose, rules and regulations, and resolutions, 1913-1940, undated (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - Photographs
    - List of photographs transferred to the Photo Archives (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - Printed Material
    - List of printed material transferred to the Library (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - Reports
    - Tenth Annual Report of the State Entomologist of Montana: Moth of the Army Cutworm, Chorizagrotis Agrestis Grote, by R. A. Cooley, 1912 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
    - King's Reports (includes tick determination, tests, tick lots), 1909, 1910 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
    - King's Journal (handwritten and typescript for 1911; typescript only for 1910), 1910, 1911 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
    - Host - Tick survey of the Bitter Root Valley, King - 1911, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
    - Old Tick Records of W. V. King, 1909-191, undated (Box-folder 3 / 11)
    - Summary and references from tick investigations at Florence, 1911-1913 (Box-folder 3 / 12-13)
    - Report to Bureau of Entomology of the Work Done by A. E. Seamans in Connection with the Spotted Fever Investigations of Bitter Root Valley, Montana, 1913 (Box-folder 3 / 14)
    - Account of Trip into West Gallatin Canon for Ticks, 1913 (Box-folder 3 / 15)
    - Staff reports (includes work done in Eastern Montana, the Bitterroot area and Carbon County, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 3 / 16)
    - Staff reports (work done in Powderville and Miles City), 1915 (Box-folder 3 / 17)
    - Reports of the Investigation and Control of the Rocky Mountain Spotted Fever Tick for the Season of 1916, by W. V. King (re work done in Bitterroot Valley) (Box-folder 3 / 18)
    - Staff reports (work done at Powderville), 1916-1917 (Box-folder 3 / 19)
    - Staff reports (includes work done at Musselshell), 1917 (Box-folder 3 / 20)
    - Staff reports (work done at Powderville and Eastern Montana), 1916-1918 (Box-folder 3 / 21)
    - Monthly and Annual Reports 1924-1930, 1924 July - 1930 June (Box-folder 3 / 22)
    - Staff monthly reports; summary of parasite work, 1926, 1929-1930 (Box-folder 3 / 23)
    - Reports - Annual - Kohls (Glen M. Kohls, laboratory assistant), 1929-1930 (Box-folder 3 / 24)
    - Reports - Morton (Fred A. Morton, laboratory assistant), 1929-1930 (Box-folder 3 / 25)
    - Monthly and Annual Reports 1931, 1930 July - 1931 June (Box-folder 3 / 26)
    - Monthly and Annual Reports 1932, 1931 July - 1932 June (Box-folder 4 / 1)
    - Monthly Reports 1933 (includes annual report and photo of Rocky Mountain spotted fever exhibit), 1932 July - 1933 June (Box-folder 4 / 2)
    - Monthly Reports 1934 (includes annual report), 1933 July - 1934 June (Box-folder 4 / 3)
    - Monthly Reports 1935 (includes annual report), 1934 July - 1935 June (Box-folder 4 / 4)
    - Monthly Reports 1936 (includes annual report and staff reports), 1935 July - 1936 June (Box-folder 4 / 5)
    - Monthly Reports 1937 (includes annual report), 1936 July - 1937 June (Box-folder 4 / 6)
    - Monthly Staff Reports 1937, 1936 July - 1937 June (Box-folder 4 / 7)
    - Monthly Reports 1938 (includes annual report), 1937 July - 1938 June (Box-folder 4 / 8)
    - Monthly Staff Reports 1938, 1937 July - 1938 June (Box-folder 4 / 9)
    - Monthly Reports 1939 (includes annual report), 1938 July - 1939 June (Box-folder 4 / 10)
    - Monthly Staff Reports 1939, 1938 July - 1939 June (Box-folder 4 / 11)
    - Monthly Reports 1940 (includes annual report), 1939 July - 1940 June (Box-folder 4 / 12)
    - Monthly Staff Reports 1940, 1939 July - 1940 June (Box-folder 4 / 13)
    - Monthly Reports 1941 (includes annual report), 1940 July - 1941 June (Box-folder 5 / 1)
    - Monthly Staff Reports 1941, 1940 July - 1941 June (Box-folder 5 / 2)
    - Monthly Reports 1941 (includes annual report), 1941 July - 1942 June (Box-folder 5 / 3)
    - Monthly Staff Reports 1941, 1941 July - 1942 June (Box-folder 5 / 4)
    - Monthly Reports 1943 (includes annual report), 1942 July - 1943 June (Box-folder 5 / 5)
    - Monthly Staff Reports 1943, 1942 July - 1943 June (Box-folder 5 / 6)
    - Monthly Reports 1944 (includes annual report), 1943 July - 1944 June (Box-folder 5 / 7)
    - Staff Reports 1944, 1943 July - 1944 June (Box-folder 5 / 8)
    - Monthly Reports 1945 (includes annual report), 1944 July - 1945 June (Box-folder 5 / 9)
    - Staff Reports 1945 (includes annual report), 1944 July - 1945 June (Box-folder 5 / 10)
    - Monthly Reports 1946 (includes annual report), 1945 July - 1946 June (Box-folder 5 / 11)
    - Staff Reports 1946, 1945 July - 1946 June (Box-folder 5 / 12)
    - Monthly Reports 1947 (includes annual report), 1946 July - 1947 June (Box-folder 5 / 13)
    - Staff Reports 1947, 1946 July - 1947 June (Box-folder 6 / 1)
  - Subject Files
    - Montana tick parasite expedition to Africa, 1928-1930 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
    - Rocky Mountain Laboratory, Hamilton (includes controversy over Laboratory location; floor plans are OVERSIZE MATERIAL), 1927-1954 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
  - Writings
    - W. J. Butler on tick parasite work, 1928 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
    - R. A. Cooley on ticks, Rocky Mountain spotted fever, tick investigations in Montana, ticks in Africa, egg laying and controlling wood ticks, 1912-1929, undated (Box-folder 6 / 7)
    - R. R. Parker on vaccination for and spread of Rocky Mountain spotted fever; tularemia; and tick investigation work in the Bitterroot Valley, undated (Box-folder 6 / 8)
    - "The Woodtick Problem in Montana and the Northwest"; "Summary Statement Regarding the Life History of Dermacentor venustus," by F. C. Bishop; "Note on Control of Ticks," by S. K. Sen; comments on the wood tick project by L. O. Howard and Royal N. Chapman; "Some Diseases of Sheep," by Dr. Hadwin; unidentified writings on ticks, Rocky Mountain spotted fever, tick paralysis in sheep, etc., 1910-1937, undated (Box-folder 6 / 9)
  - Miscellany
    - Blueprints of Building for Tick and Spotted Fever Work; drawing of laboratory grounds [OVERSIZE MATERIAL], undated (Box-folder 6 /)
    - Inventory for Bitter Root Field Station equipment, tools, etc, 1925, 1930, 1938 (Box-folder 6 / 10)
    - List of artifacts transferred to the Museum, undated (Box-folder 6 / 11)
    - Memorial to William Gittinger and Arthur Kerlee; R. A. Cooley resume, 1929, undated (Box-folder 6 / 12)
    - Rocky Mountain spotted fever case distribution and patient data, 1905-1934 (Box-folder 6 / 13)
  - Clippings
    - Rocky Mountain spotted fever, parasite studies, vaccine development, laboratory in Hamilton, etc, 1908-1943 (Box-folder 6 / 14)
- Montana State Board of Health
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondence between T. D. Tuttle and H. T. Ricketts and others re Rocky Mountain spotted fever, 1908-1912 (Box-folder 6 / 15)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence re closing of laboratory, other diseases, etc., 1919-1957 (Box-folder 6 / 16)
    - Correspondence re acquisition by the Rocky Mountain Laboratory of the Dr. P. Schultz tick collection and literature, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 6 / 17)
  - Financial Records
    - Bills of Dr. T. B. McClintic for laboratory animals, etc., 1912 (Box-folder 6 / 18)
  - Maps
    - List of maps transferred to Library Map Collection, undated (Box-folder 6 / 19)
  - Reports
    - "Report of the activities of the State Board of Health in controlling the epidemic of typhoid in Helena"; "Polio vaccine usage and distribution report"; field trip report; animals used report, 1929-1956 (Box-folder 6 / 20)
  - Subject Files
    - Bubonic plague, 1935-1939 (Box-folder 6 / 21)
    - Health conditions on Montana Indian reservations (includes studies of trachoma), 1925-1944 (Box-folder 6 / 22)
    - Leprosy, 1918-1939 (Box-folder 6 / 23)
    - Montana Public Health Association (includes papers given at meetings re tuberculosis, Indian Reservations conditions, scarlet fever, botulism, cancer, cattle diseases, vitamins, venereal diseases, plague, encephalitis, industrial hygiene, nutrition, etc.), 1914-1940 (Box-folder 6 / 24-26)
    - Montana Tuberculosis Society; Montana Trudeau Society; Montana Thoracic Society, 1955-1966 (Box-folder 6 / 27)
    - "Pediatric evaluation of Indian children in Great Falls" (re Hill 57), 1959-1960 (Box-folder 6 / 28)
    - Rocky Mountain Spotted Fever Committee of American Public Health Association, Western Branch, circa 1930 (Box-folder 6 / 29)
    - State Board of Health, Rocky Mountain Spotted Fever Conference (includes papers presented at the conference), 1923 (Box-folder 6 / 30)
  - Miscellany
    - Histories of the Montana State Board of Health and the study of Rocky Mountain Spotted Fever, undated (Box-folder 6 / 31)
    - Resolutions re Public Health League of Montana; U. S. Bureau of Entomology, 1911, undated (Box-folder 6 / 32)
    - List of county and local health officers (includes salary, appointment, etc.), 1929 (Box-folder 6 / 33)